Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Interview: Gottlieb, Sanford, 2013 April 12; MS2388
  Keywords provided by the donor for Sanford Gottlieb interview: American University School of International Service, National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy, SANE, Brooklyn, Father con-man, federal prison, mail fraud, Great Depression, Abyssinia, Ethiopia, Hitler, Japanse militarism, City College New York, Brooklyn College, Navy, Dartmouth College, Married 1947, Paris 5 years, School of Political Science — Paris, Doctoral Sorbonne, Joe McCarthy, Correspondent French news weekly, Labor movement, Organizer 2 local unions New York, International Typographical Union, Labor's Daily, International Union Electrical Workers, AFSCME sellout, National Committee for A Sane Nuclear Policy, SANE, Nuclear testing — U.S. and Soviet Union, Newspaper ads for SANE/nuclear testing, Washington, D.C. SANE affiliate group, SANE political action director, Grassroots campaign to end all nuclear tests, SANE executive director in 1967, Cold War mindset, Soviet Union, Pacifists, World Federalists, World government, Joe McCarthy, Congressional witch hunts, Working for peace- analogous to traitors in public mind, Friends Committee on National Legislation, United Church of Christ, Unitarians, Nuclear test-ban treaty, Women's Strike for Peace, Direct-action, Peace movement was minority, President Kennedy, Cautious, but open, Democrat, Norman Cousins, Saturday Review of Literature, Cousins influenced Kennedy, Partial test-ban treaty passed, Nuclear tests banned atmosphere, under water, Radioactive fallout, Series ads New York Times, Dr. Benjamin Spock ad, Dangers of fallout, Dr. Homer Jack, Unitarian minister, Kennedy coalition for test-ban treaty, United Auto Workers, National Farmers Union, Public trusted government until Vietnam, Kennedy American University speech June 1963, Called for an end to the Cold War, Soviet Union, Spread of nuclear weapons, Arms race, Lyndon Johnson, Vietnam, Tonkin Gulf incident, escalation, SANE sought negotiated settlement, 1964 SANE petition for neutral North and South Vietnam, Professor Hans Morgenthau, Bernard Fall, Bombing of North Vietnam, Dr. Spock, Professor H. Stuart Hughes, Telegram to LBJ, SANE in moderate wing of antiwar movement, SDS, Students for a Democratic Society, First antiwar rally April 1965, SANE sponsored first non-student, anti-war march on Washington, November 1965, Coalition of SANE and more radical and moderate groups, 35,000 attended, Sylvan Theater, Washington Monument, Norman Thomas, Coretta Scott King, Edwin Dahlberg, American Northern Baptist Convention, Negotiated peace in Vietnam, Immediate pullout of troops, Vietcong flags, Pro-Chinese Communist group, Tried to keep them out, New York Times, Washington Post, Mainstream press focused on middle-class participants, Radical wing increasing in numbers, Street action vs. electoral action, TV covered most flamboyant forms of protest, Flag burnings, 1968 majority against war, 1968 majority also against war protesters, Middle America, patriotism, Youth revolt against authority, "Silent Majority", Richard Nixon, Hubert Humphrey, Norman Cousins, Ghost-writer for Humphrey in 1960, Senate Disarmament Subcommittee chairman, Humphrey became lapdog of LBJ, Humphrey denounced student protestors, November 1965 — Cousins, Homer Jack, Gottlieb met with VP Humphrey, Humphrey attacked students protesters, Reminded him of Commies he used to know in Minneapolis, Not in '50s anymore; not in Minneapolis, anymore, Students aren't commies, Washington Post, Vietnam Day Committee, Dump Johnson Movement, Allard Lowenstein, Endorsed Eugene McCarthy, New Hampshire, Bobby Kennedy, George McGovern, Assassinations of Martin Luther King, Bobby Kennedy, "Peace plank" at Democratic National Convention 1968, Chicago police riot, Public supported police, Hubert Humphrey, Richard Nixon, Dr. Spock split from SANE 1967, Spock wanted to be bolder, less cautious, SANE board division over who to protest with, Spock said demonstrate with anybody, Spock left board in split, Ran for president 1972, Julius Hobson Spock runningmate, Marcus Raskin, William Sloane Coffin, Dr. Spock indicted, Allegedly conseled draft resistance, SANE/Freeze, Indictment chill through antiwar movement, Freedom of Information Act, FBI at SANE's meetings, Informers, Army Intelligence, CIA, Opened one piece of domestic mail, SANE on Nixon's "enemies list", National Liberation Front (NLF), First French Indochina War, Paris lived with Vietnamese students, Vietnamese nationalism, Invasions from China, Japanese invasion, Occupation by French, Bernard Fall, American Friends Service Committee, South Vietnam, Went with clergy on fact-finding trip South Vietnam 1965, Saturday Review, Norman Cousins, Algiers, Paris, Met diplomats National Liberation Front, Vietcong, White House, North and South Vietnamese Communists, Algiers, Prague, Moscow, Warsaw, U.S. botched 1966 peace effort, North Vietnam, Lyndon Johnson, Richard Nixon, Expanded war to Cambodia, Moratorium — 1969, Moderate students in antiwar movement, Sam Brown and others, Organize communities stop work, stop classes, Demonstrations, debates, lectures, Nixon administration, War Powers Act, SANE role in, SANE opposed increased military spending, arms race, Opposed B-1 bomber, anti-ballistic missile system (ABM), Soviet Union, Cuban Missile Crisis 1962, University of Michigan, Marcus Raskin called, Soviet missiles in Cuba, "A dangerous leaker", United Nations, Patriotism, National security, Threats to the United States, Need recognize threats without exaggerating threats, Not automatically resort military force, Left SANE 1977, New Directions organization, Panama Canal treaty, Reagan period, United Campuses Against Nuclear War (UCAN), Stundet/faculty teach-ins, Union of Concerned Scientists, Center for Defense Information, Admiral Eugene LaRocque, America's Defense Monitor — war/peace issues, PBS stations, Vietnam, Radical forms of protest, Movement neutralized, Did not end the war, Prevented some of worst of Johnson administration potential excesses, Didn't bomb dikes in Vietnam, Richard Nixon, Silent Majority, Nuclear testing period, Major goal partially achieved, Small coalition on nuclear treaty, JFK receptive, Feminist movement.
- Interview: Grosman, Art, 2013 January 24; MS2388
  A civil rights and antiwar activist while a student at Howard University in the early 1960s, Art Grosman made his biggest mark on local activism beginning in 1966 as one of the co-founders of the Washington Free Press. The WFP was the first and most influential D.C. underground newspaper for almost 4 years, folding after constantly being subjected to police suppression, infiltrators, and FBI pressures against printers.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Art Grosman interview: Turkey, Mediterranean Sea, Grosman parents immigrants, Ukraine, Japanese, Poland, Nebraska, B'nai B'rith, Orthodox Jewish school, FDR administration, Democrats, voting rights D.C., Hebrew Academy, trees in Israel, Palestinian, Army-McCarthy hearing, Sears (& Roebuck), Howard University, studied physics, voter registration, Mississippi, Texas, 4th and Decatur Streets, blockbusting, Chevy Chase, D.C., Lafayette (Elementary School), Alice Deal (Junior High School), Wilson (High School), Old Soldiers Home, Ben's Chili Bowl, League of Women Voters, Mississippi, Cold War, Russians, conscientious objector, Howard U., ROTC, ACLU, Peace Club (Howard U.), Army, Vietnam, the draft, Washington Free Press, General (Lewis) Hershey, Selective Service System, civil rights, Frank Speltz (WFP co-founder), Tasso's Bar, George Washington University (GWU), intercollegiate newspaper, Catholic University, American University, George Washington University, Georgetown University, University of Maryland, Trinity College, Dick Ochs, Sheila Ryan, Gabe Huck, Tony Gittens, Woody (NO LAST NAME), SDS (Students for a Democratic Society), Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party), Atlantic City (Democratic convention), Howard University, Fairmont Street/Girard Street slumlord, Washington Free Press, communists (of all shades), Coca-Cola, Maoists, Leninists, taxi driver, Washington Free Press first office, 1727 or 1737 Q Street NW, Carla (artist, NO LAST NAME), 10,000 copies at first, 30,000 later, maybe 100,000, John Hagerhorst, Frederick (Md.), (Washington) Free Press, advertisers, hippie shops, head shops, bars, big ads record companies, federal government.
- Interview: Hanrahan, Debby, 2016 October 28; MS2388
  Debby Hanrahan has a 50-plus-year history of local activism in civil rights, social justice and antiwar campaigns. From the '60s and '70s, these include the continuing decades-long fight for D.C. statehood; the successful citizen campaign to stop destructive freeways through the heart of D.C.; the local organizing around the United Farmworkers Union grape boycott. Since then, her activism has included local public school advocacy; successful petitioning for statehood, nuclear freeze and medical marijuana ballot initiatives; and rallying and marching repeatedly against U.S. wars and for whistleblowers.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Debby Hanrahan interview: Bethesda, Maryland, Chevy Chase, Maryland, ambassador, Iran, "Negro problem", Dick Abel, Walt Whitman High School, Skidmore College, Senator Saltonstall, Rep. James Corman, March on Washington, Danville, Virginia, Martin Luther King, mass arrests, Larry Aaronsen, Peace Corps, President Kennedy, John Coyne, Ethiopia, Temuco (Chile), rural mobile birth control project, Dr. Lopez, IUDs, Mapuche Indians, plantation owners, rubella, class system, Peace Corps, Eduardo Frei, mothers' center, sewing machines, AID, (Frank Barger) father ill, Dump Johnson movement, Al Lowenstein, Bella Abzug, Harold Ickes, Curtis Gans, Julius Hobson, Al Lowenstein, Long Island, Eugene McCarthy, Bobby Kennedy, George McGovern, Al Lowenstein, Harold Ickes, Dump Johnson movement, Eugene McCarthy, Julius Hobson, Suzie Solf, Julius Hobson, Hobson v. Hansen lawsuit, equalize school expenditures, track system, Dunbar High School, Julius Hobson, Marxist, atheist, Hobson gimmicks, rat problem, Georgetown, Anacostia, freeway fight, Sammie Abbott, Marion Barry, Reginald Booker, Julius Hobson, Charles Cassell, paddy wagon, North Central Freeway, Brookland, Sammie Abbott, elected school board, non-voting delegate to Congress, D.C. Statehood Party, Lou Aronica, Josephine Butler, labor organizer, D.C. Lung Association, D.C. Statehood Party central committee, Ed Guinan, statehood initiative, constitutional convention, Mitch Snyder, Center for Creative Non-violence (CCNV), Rich Bruning, Ward 1, D.C. constitution, 1968, Brint Dillingham, Compeers, Grape Boycott, Eugene McCarthy, Chicago Democratic Convention, housing, civil rights, John Dillingham, Catholics, National Guard, Grant Park, police riot, Dick Gregory, Clinton Bamberger, Catholic University Law School, "Fuck Mayor Dailey", tear gas, Maryland delegation hospitality suite, Maryland House Speaker Thomas Hunter Lowe, Brint Dillingham, Compeers, Freedom House, Washington Free Press, grape boycott, blood on grapes, Giant supermarket, Michael Tabor, picket lines, Safeway, Brint Dillingham, John Dillingham, Santa Claus suits, International Safeway, Martha Tabor, Dupont Circle, Freedom House, Washington Free Press, Montgomery County police, Circuit Court, grand jury investigation, anti-war movement, St. Thomas Church, Joe Forer, Ober Law, anti-free speech, McCarthy era, Hilda Mason, D.C. public schools, Charlie Mason, Lawrence Guyot, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, StandUp for Democracy (organization), Lawrence Guyot, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Freedom Summer, Lawrence Guyot, All Souls Unitarian Church, Hilda Mason, Charles Mason, Lawrence Guyot, hippie trail, London to Nepal, Rep. Yvonne Braithwaite Burke, Washington Post, Local Pressmen's Union, Washington Post, Josephine Butler, Alaska, grand jury investigation, 5th amendment, Jim Dugan, Joe Forer, David Rein, Jim Dugan, Hilda Mason, University of the District of Columbia Law School, clinical public-interest approach to law, D.C. City Council, David Clarke, Hilda Mason, John Wilson, Wilhelmina Rolark, Howard University Law School, Washington Post, Charlie Mason, UDC Law School, Wayne Turner, Chris Otten, Mark Borbely, nuclear freeze initiative, Susan Abbott, Leonard Bernstein, Hubert Leckie, Washington National Cathedral, Barbara Hendricks, Jessye Norman, Leonard Bernstein.
- Interview: Hanrahan, John, 2016 June 02; MS2388
  Former Washington Post reporter/union activist in support of 1975 pressmen's strike at the Post; also a DC community activist on voting rights, other local issues.
  Keywords provided by the donor for John Hanrahan interview: Childhood, Iowa, unions, progressive, conservative, local newspaper, 1958-1960 university, the draft, Ft. Jackson, Army journalist, Davenport newspaper, Washington DC, plentiful jobs, Montgomery Sentinel, Washington Star, Washington Post, Mike Tabor, 1965, ACCESS, the Dillinghams, Debby, 1968 Democratic Convention, grape boycott, 1970, Honor America Day, "Fuck Billy Graham", tear gas, 1972 Debby & John travel for a year overland to India, Washington Post goes public, "school for scabs", 1971 walkout by pressmen, 1974 withholding of excellence, newspaper guild panics, guild meeting Oct 1, 1975, pressmen damaged machinery ?…NO ! but the presses could not operate, newspaper guild meeting, class conflict, control of the pressroom, picket lines, line crossers, many go back, pressmen suffer, AFL-CIO no help, DC Council supports, life as a free-lancer, books, Lost Frontier, Government by Contract, local activism, Statehood Party, stadium give-aways, McMillan Park, newspaper ad, dinner with Donnie Graham, support in Congress, errors in reporting, Sam Smith, All the President's Men, Esquire 1977 "Last Angry Men", Carl Bernstein, Eugene Debs, Brint Dillingham, funniest man in the world.
- Interview: Harrington, Richard, 2013 February 08; MS2388
  Editor of alternative publications Woodwind and Unicorn Times, chronicler of D.C. music scene for more than 40 years with first the alternative press and then the Washington Post.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Richard Harrington interview: Journalist, schooling, dropout, folk singer, Garret Players Susan Sarandon, Lorton, Washington Star, Unicorn Times, Washington Post fulltime 1980, McClean Gardens, Glen Echo, Quicksilver Times, CIA plant, hippies v. activists, Georgetown counter-culture, sex drugs and rock and roll, Washington Free Clinic, Woodwind, arts newspaper, Quicksilver Times editor, Bohemian Caverns, Cellar Door, Childe Harold, local musicians, Emergency.
- Interview: Hassan, Sandra Barrett, 2013 April 26; MS2388
  Third generation Washingtonian who was a Howard University civil rights activist, later an education and community organizer. Met Malcom X at the 1963 March for Jobs and Freedom. Also an artist and maker of quilts that chronicle the civil rights movement.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Sandy Barrett Hassan inteview: Sandra Barrett Hassan, Washington DC, Northeast, Negro, segregated school, petition, Ivy City, swimming at Union Station, black areas, Western High School, activist parents, Howard University, Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, testing restaurants in Virginia, March on Washington, Malcolm X, African Heritage Dancers and Drummers, 1968 riots, Julius Hobson.
- Interview: Herz, Lillian Peterson, 2019 May 17; MS2388
  Biography
  Information provided by the donor: Lillian Peterson Herz discusses her pacifist upbringing and beliefs that led to her involvement in the civil rights movement, including SNCC voter registration campaigns in Georgia and Mississippi, and efforts to end the war in Vietnam.
  Keywords provided the donor: Georgetown University School of Foreign Service, arrived 1965, first group of women, pacifist family upbringing, disabled father, Paradise California, high school civics teacher Virginia Franklin taught all forms of government, John Birch society, social justice, civil rights, Georgetown University Community Action Program, tutoring, Albany Georgia, SNCC, voter registration, Bob Jackel – Jesuit priest, Anne Gallivan, bus boycott, O. Roy Chalk, racism, economic divisions, home rule, foreign policy – self interest vs building a better world, Southwest Georgia voting project, SNCC Freedom House, Moultrie Georgia, black fear, white power structure, Sunflower County Mississippi, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Fannie Lou Hamer, caring community, mass meetings, constitutional rights, Father McSorley, seminar on just war, alternatives to war, just peace, reaffirmed pacifism and social justice, Healy Hall, anti-Vietnam War, teach-ins, speak-outs, Bill Clinton – student leader at Georgetown, Mobilization Against the War rally 1967 – New York City, Pentagon March 1967, draft burnings, endless wars, movement vs lifestyles, live your lifestyle, construction, home improvement, social worker, AFDC – Aid to Families with Dependent Children, NWRO – National Welfare Rights Organization, institutionalized racism, Vietnam veteran, fixed homes of poor people, profit sharing, Desert Storm, Peace Resource Center, 9/11, Cuba,-1999, Pastors for Peace, Code Pink, ANSWER Coalition, Venezuelan Embassy, U.S. lawlessness.
- Interview: Hilda Mason Remembered, 2010 May 09; MS2388
  Hilda (1916-2007) and Charles (Charlie) Mason are remembered by Lawrence Guyot and Debbie Hanrahan - donated to the Lessons of the Sixties Project by the D.C. Statehood Green Party. Hilda and Charlie were Washington, D.C.'s most significant activist couple from the early 1960s to the 2000s. From the time they were married until their deaths 40-some years later, Hilda -- the public school teacher and assistant principal and great granddaughter of a slave -- and Charlie -- the government civil servant, later attorney, and heir to a sizable fortune -- were seldom referred to in the singular; to those in the activist and electoral politics communities, they were always one entity -- Hilda and Charlie.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Hilda Mason interview: DC Statehood Green Party, Hilda Howland Mason, civil rights movement, environmental movement, anti-nuclear movement, Debby Hanrahan, Lawrence Guyot, Mississippi, Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), Freedom Summer, Hattiesburg Missisissippi, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP), Guyot chair of MFDP, Democratic National Convention 1964, Atlantic City New Jersey, ANC commissioner, Winona Mississippi, Fanny Lou Hamer, "Pillar of Fire" book, Taylor Branch, SNCC, Marion Barry, Elizabeth Levy, Charlie and Hilda Mason, Fannie Lou Hamer, Charlie Mason, All-Souls Unitarian Church, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Parsty (MFDP), Guyot/MFDP "too radical" for church, Hilda threatens to leave church, Guyot allowed to speak, DC Council, 1964-1968 movement into electoral politics, values of civil rights movement, left depended on Hilda Mason, David Clarke School of Law (University of the District of Columbia), Hilda/Charlie kept it alive, Washington Post opposed, Hilda ran to keep school opened, Ranked 10 of 188 for public interest law, 51% minority student body, U.S. News & World Report rankings, UDC Law School ranked first for progressive students, Attracts community organizers, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Fund-raiser at All Souls Uitarian Church, Raised $4000 for bail, Elizabeth Levy, (Rep. Robert) Kastenmeier, ANCs (Advisory Neighborhood Commissions, Hilda Mason, Julius Hobson, Josephine Butler, D.C. Statehood Green Party, D.C. Constitutional Convention, Bottle bill, Nuclear freeze, D.C. School Board, Charlie Mason, Ivanhoe Donaldson, Josephine Butler, Hilda's grandson Nestor, Contributions to organizations, Never expected anything in return, Ella Baker, Saved the UDC law school, Mayor Tony Williams, Models for philanthropy, Moved easily from activism to politics, Book "Hilda", By Caroline Nicholas (daughter), DC City Council, DC Youth Orchestra, Nurses in schools, Howard University Law School, Fannie Lou Hamer, Ella Baker, Septima Clark, Josephine Butler, Maine, Hilda/Charlie partnership, Set ethical standard, Josephine Butler, Russia, Margaret and Al McSurely, Senate Internal Security Subcommittee, Pike County Kentucky, Center for Constitutional Rights, Charlie financed the case, Guyot's religious beliefs, Empower people, Hilda Mason, Ella Baker, Guyot police beatings, SNCC, Community organizing, Racial Reconciliation organization, Oxford Mississipi, Tallahatchie County Mississippi, Taylor Branch, Philadelphia Missisippi, Macomb Mississippi, School bombings, Role of religion, Guyot's ongoing projects, Successful movements, Empowerment, Same-sex marriage, Free and independent Palestine, Comprehensive immigration.
- Interview: Hobson, Tina (Part 1), 2013 May 03; MS2388
  An environmental and clean energy activist, Tina spent many years in various government posts in which she promoted civil rights, improved equal opportunities for women in the federal government, and worked with employment and training programs to assist the poor. During her interview for the Lessons of the 60s project, Tina spoke extensively about her late husband, Julius Hobson, the famed D.C. civil rights leader (and later D.C. Council member), whose leadership was most responsible for ending discrimination in hiring in local retail stores and in overturning racially discriminatory practices in the city's public schools.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Tina Hobson interview: Julius Hobson, Birmingham, Alabama, World War II, Howard University, Masters in economics, DC Chapter Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), Ran picket lines retailers, Desegregation created 5,000 jobs, Anti-freeway fight, Hobson v. Hansen lawsuit, Track system, D.C. Statehood Party, Antiwar activities, Vice presidential candidate to Dr. Benjamin Spock 1972, She born in Seattle, Lived China, Stanford University, President Kennedy, Washington, D.C., Met Julius Hobson 1967, National Institute of Public Affairs, Ford Foundation, Hobson v. Hansen case, D.C.'s appointed City Council, Mayor Walter Washington, DC Board of Education, Married in 1969, "The Damned Children", Blackest kids in lowest tracks, Teachers and Hobson v Hansen, Sterling Tucker, Equalization school resources, Civil Service Commission, Babies segregated in hospitals, O.C. Hall, Washington Hospital Center, Black churches, Civil Service Commission, Department of Energy, Always well-dressed, fedora, Excellent cook, Didn't drink, Cleaned the house, Ironed own shirts, Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), Loved opera, Army in Italy, Elected school board at-large, Lost school board reelection, Civil Service Commission (CSC), Federal women's program at CSC, Discrimination against women, Julius "blind spot", Discrimination against women, federal discrimination lawsuit, African-Americans, other minorities, women, Peace marches, Bermuda, Marriage more acceptable to white, than black, community, Julius and Tom Hayden.
- Interview: Hobson, Tina (Part 2), 2018 February 13; MS2388
- Interview: Huff, Julie, 2016 August 11; MS2388
  Julie Huff grew up in Birmingham, Alabama and Atlanta, Georgia in the 1950s and 1960s. Exposure to segregation, the civil rights movement in the early 1960s and the anti-war movement led her to a lifetime of activism for civil rights and women's rights and against the vietnam war, beginning in high school and continuing in the Washington, D.C. area following college. She later became a nurse and worked in women's health and public health for over 30 years.